<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="PV_characterIndex_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <head>
        <editor>Anthony</editor>
        <co-editor>Mia</co-editor>
        <source
            ref="https://www.bowers.org/index.php/collection/collection-blog/who-s-who-in-the-popol-vuh"/>
        <source ref="https://www.litcharts.com/lit/popol-vuh/characters"/>
        <source ref="https://www.historyonthenet.com/the-mayan-pantheon-gods-and-goddesses"/>
        <source ref="https://ancientmayalife.blogspot.com/2012/11/kawil-god-k.html"/>
        <source ref="https://mayanpeninsula.com/mayan-gods/"/>
        <source ref="http://www.teachinghistory100.org/objects/about_the_object/maize_god"/>
        <source ref="https://jacquescoulardeau.medium.com/male-exclusive-blood-sacrifice-in-maya-religion-82319e95dd2d"/>
        <source ref="https://www.thoughtco.com/maya-gods-and-goddesses-117947"/>
    </head>
    <index>
        <character xml:id="SPS" inPV="true">
            <name>Sovereign Plumed Serpent</name>
            
            <altName>Kukulkan</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/SPSerpent.jpg"/>
            <entity>God</entity>
            <of>Heart of Sky</of>
            <desc>Sovereign Plumed Serpent is a feathered serpent god very similar to Quetzalcoatl
                of the Aztecs. In the Quiché language his name is Tepeu Gucumatz and it’s actually
                the first place we come to a translation issue, as often in previous translations
                Tepeu and Gucumatz were translated as two separate gods. He is also part of the
                group that, in three separate stages, creates men out of three different materials:
                mud, which dissolves into nothingness; wood, which fails to respect the gods and is
                destroyed for it; and lastly, maize, which succeeds in creating the people we know
                today. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Hur" inPV="true">
            <name>Hurricane</name>
            <altName>Thunderbolt Hurricane</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Hurricane.jpg"/>
            <entity>God</entity>
            <of>Heart of Sky</of>
            <desc>Hurricane is the leader of the three thunder gods that together are Heart of Sky
                (sometimes called Heart of Sky, Heart of Earth). The god is often called One-Legged
                because in most depictions he has one human leg and a serpent’s tail. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Xpi" inPV="true">
            <name>Xpiyacoc</name>
            <altName>Grandfather</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Xpiyacoc.jpg"/>
            <entity>God</entity>
            <family>
                <partner idref="#Xmu">Xmucane</partner>
                <children>
                    <son idref="#OneH">One Hunahpu</son>
                    <son idref="#SevH">Seven Hunahpu</son>
                </children>
                <grandChildren>
                    <grandson idref="#Hun">Hunahpu</grandson>
                    <grandson idref="#Xba">Xbalanque</grandson>
                    <grandson idref="#OneMonk">One Monkey</grandson>
                    <grandson idref="#OneArt">One Artisan</grandson>
                </grandChildren>
            </family>
            <desc>Xpiyacoc and Xmucane referred to as a pair almost always in epithet are the two
                oldest gods of the Quiché-Maya pantheon. This doesn’t end up being as successful as
                any of the gods would like, so the pair also helps create the final version of man,
                maize men. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Xmu" inPV="true">
            <name>Xmucane</name>
            <altName>Grandmother</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Xmucane.jpg"/>
            <entity>diety</entity>
            <family>
                <partner idref="#Xpi">Xpiyacoc</partner>
                <children>
                    <son idref="#OneH">One Hunahpu</son>
                    <son idref="#SevH">Seven Hunahpu</son>
                </children>
                <grandChildren>
                    <grandson idref="#Hun">Hunahpu</grandson>
                    <grandson idref="#Xba">Xbalanque</grandson>
                    <grandson idref="#OneMonk">One Monkey</grandson>
                    <grandson idref="#OneArt">One Artisan</grandson>
                </grandChildren>
            </family>
            <desc>Xpiyacoc and Xmucane referred to as a pair almost always in epithet are the two
                oldest gods of the Quiché-Maya pantheon. This doesn’t end up being as successful as
                any of the gods would like, so the pair also helps create the final version of man,
                maize men. Xmucane even grinds the maize from which the first men are made. </desc>
        </character>
        <!--<character xml:id="MudM" inPV="true">
            <name>Mud Men</name>
            
            <desc>The mud men were the Bearer, Begetter’s first attempt at making man. They were
                drawn from mud, which sadly did not hold shape. The creatures seemed to dissolve at
                their inception, and though they had the ability to speak they said only nonsense.
                Their forms were also lopsided, as they did not set and could not reproduce. So in
                disappointment, the gods left the mud men to dwindle until they were nothing.
            </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="WoodM">
            <name>Wooden Men</name>
            <desc>After the failure of the mud men, Heart of Sky and Bearer, Begetter decide that it
                would be prudent to get assistance in their creation of man, so they enlist the help
                of Xpiyacoc and Xmucane. The result is wooden men or mannequins, people carved out
                of wood that moved and spoke and multiplied. However, they had no minds and no
                hearts, nor did they have blood. They did not give the thanks that their creators
                desired so Hurricane destroyed them in a flood. The survivors were attacked by the
                creatures they had once eaten for food and were horribly disfigured. The few that
                got away became monkeys and still live in the forests today. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="MazM">
            <name>Maize Men</name>
            <desc>The first men from which we all descend were made from maize and water by Heart of
                Sky; Bearer, Begetter; Xpiyacoc and Xmucane. The maker gods searched for a long time
                to find the ingredient from which man was to be made when finally it was brought to
                them by the animals they had made: maize. A fox, coyote, parrot, and crow brought
                news of yellow and white corn. When the gods arrived at the source Xmucane ground it
                up and the gods formed the first men. At first the gods gave maize men the ability
                of unlimited sight, so that they could see and understand everything in the
                universe. But the gods themselves feared what they had created and so they dullened
                their vision, allowing them to only see what was in front of them. The first men did
                everything we do; they talked, looked, and listened, thought, moved, and worked.
                Most importantly they gave thanks to the gods. </desc>
        </character>-->
        <character xml:id="Hun" inPV="true">
            <name>Hunahpu</name>
            <altName>One Blowgun Hunter</altName>
            <altName>Venus Lord</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/HeroTwins.jpg"/>
            <entity>Hero Twins</entity>
            <family>
                <parents>
                    <father idref="#OneH">One Hunahpu</father>
                    <mother idref="#BW">Blood Woman</mother>
                </parents>
                <uncle idref="#SevH">Seven Hunahpu</uncle>
                <brother idref="#Xba">Xbalanque</brother>
                <brother idref="#OneArt">One Artisan</brother>
                <brother idref="#OneMonk">One Monkey</brother>
                <grandparents>
                    <grandma idref="#Xmu">Xmucane</grandma>
                    <grandpa idref="#Xpi">Xpiyacoc</grandpa>
                </grandparents>
            </family>
            <desc>
                Hunahpu is one of the hero twins in the Popol Vuh. Both brothers were intelligent,
                brave, handsome, and had magical powers; all necessary traits for their role as the
                heroic protagonists for the Popol Vuh. With his brother, Xbalanque, he rids the pre-human world of all manner of villainous gods, including Seven Macaw, Zipacna, One Death, and Seven Death. Hunahpu is a skilled trickster and is referred to by the narrator as genius. Though the twins are physically strong and are skilled at physical pursuits such as playing ball and shooting birds with blowguns, their genius is their most important asset and is the primary reason why the twins are so successful in ridding the world of evil. Hunahpu's genius is apparent even before his birth, when the narrator suggests that he and Xbalanque are responsible for leaving signs that allow his grandmother, Xmucane, to understand that Blood Moon is telling the truth about the twins' immaculate conception. Their father is One Hunahpu, and the twins are conceived when he spits into Blood Moon's hand. After the twins sacrifice One and Seven Death, they ascend to the sky with the Four Hundred Boys to become the moon and sun.
            </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Xba" inPV="true">
            <name>Xbalanque</name>
            
            <altName>Young Hidden Sun</altName>
            <altName>Jaguar Sun</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Hero_Twins.JPG"/>
            <entity>Hero Twins</entity>
            <family>
                <parents>
                    <father idref="#OneH">One Hunahpu</father>
                    <mother idref="#BW">Blood Woman</mother>
                </parents>
                <uncle idref="#SevH">Seven Hunahpu</uncle>
                <brother idref="#Hun">Hunahpu</brother>
                <brother idref="#OneArt">One Artisan</brother>
                <brother idref="#OneMonk">One Monkey</brother>
                <grandparents>
                    <grandma idref="#Xmu">Xmucane</grandma>
                    <grandpa idref="#Xpi">Xpiyacoc</grandpa>
                </grandparents>
            </family>
            <desc>Xbalanque is one of the hero twins in the Popol Vuh. He and his twin, Hunahpu, dedicate their lives to taking down any characters who seek to "magnify themselves" and attempt to appear more powerful than they actually are. The twins are very strong and excel in their physical pursuits. In particular, the boys are very good at playing a traditional Mesoamerican ball game, just like their father and uncle One Hunahpu and Seven Hunahpu were before their deaths. Despite this, however, Xbalanque and Hunahpu's greatest assets are their smarts and their ability to lay traps and tricks for others, while also seeing through their adversaries' tricks. In particular, this is how Xbalanque and Hunahpu best One Death and Seven Death. After this, the boys leave earth for the sky, where they become the moon and sun. 
            </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="PBD" inPV="true">
            <name>Seven Macaw</name>
            <altName>Principal Bird Diety</altName>
            <altName>Wuqub Kaquix</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Seven_Macaw.jpg"/>
            <entity>God</entity>
            <family>
                <children>
                    <son idref="#Zip">Zipacna</son>
                    <son idref="#Ear">Earthquake</son>
                </children>
            </family>
            <desc>Seven Macaw Is a highly prideful god who is often compared to Lucifer by scholars
                of the Popol Vuh. The brightly colored Macaw demon-god is also the father of both
                Zipacna and Earthquake, who both share his arrogance. He incurs the wrath of Heart
                of Sky by declaring himself to be both the sun and the moon to the wooden men.
            </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Zip" inPV="true">
            <name>Zipacna</name>
            <img src="images/characterPics/zipacna.jpeg"/>
            <entity>Demon God</entity>
            <family>
                <parents>
                    <father idref="#SevM">Seven Macaw</father>
                </parents>
                <brother idref="#Ear">Earthquake</brother>
            </family>
            <desc> Zipacna (or Sipac) is a celestial crocodile warrior, considered a counterpart of the pan-Mesoamerican god Cipactli, the earth-monster, who had to be killed to create the earth. Known mainly from the 16th-century highland account of the Popol Vuh, Zipacna also appears in oral traditions of rural towns in highland Maya regions.
                
                According to the Popol Vuh, Zipacna was the maker of mountains, who spent his days looking for crabs and fishes to eat, and his nights lifting up the mountains.
                One of the demonic sons of Seven Macaw, Zipacna was known as the crust of the
                earth. He had the power to create mountains overnight. Like his father though he is
                too prideful and similar to his father. As his father claims to be the sun and the
                moon, he claims to be the creator of the earth. He outsmarts the Four Hundred Boys when they try to kill him by burying him in a deep hole, and when they're too drunk to fight back, Zipacna brings their hut down on them and kills them all. Hunahpu and Xbalanque take revenge by starving Zipacna for two days, and then setting a trap for him by placing a fake crab under an overhang at the foot of a mountain. When Zipacna wiggles into the small space to get the crab, the mountain rests on his chest and he turns to stone.
            </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Ear" inPV="true">
            <name>Earthquake</name>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Earth_and_Zipac.jpg"/>
            <entity>Demon God</entity>
            <family>
                <parents>
                    <father idref="#SevM">Seven Macaw</father>
                </parents>
                <brother idref="#Zip">Zipacna</brother>
            </family>
            <desc>Earthquake is the other demonic son of Seven Macaw. As his name suggests he is the
                god of earthquakes, causing mountains to move with the tap of his foot. Like his
                brother and father, he is prideful.  Hurricane instructs Hunahpu and Xbalanque to trick Earthquake into sitting down somewhere in the east, which the twins do by telling Earthquake that there's a massive mountain in the east. As they travel, Hunahpu and Xbalanque coat a bird in plaster and give it to Earthquake to eat. This causes Earthquake to lose the strength in his arms and legs, and the twins bury him in the earth.</desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="OneH" inPV="true">
            <name>One Hunahpu</name>
            <altName>Maize God</altName>
            <altName>Hun Hunahpu</altName>
            <altName>God E</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/maize_god.png"/>
            <entity>God</entity>
            <family>
                <parents>
                    <mother idref="#Xmu">Xmucane</mother>
                    <father idref="#Xpi">Xpiyacoc</father>
                </parents>
                <children>
                    <son idref="#OneMonk">One Monkey</son>
                    <son idref="#OneArt">One Artisan</son>
                    <son idref="#Hun">Hunahpu</son>
                    <son idref="#Xba">Xbalanque</son>
                </children>
                <babymom>Xbaquiyalo</babymom>
                <babymom idref="#BW">Lady Blood</babymom>
                <brother idref="#SevH">Seven Hunahpu</brother>
            </family>
            <desc>The maize god, Hun Hunahpu, was one of the most important owing to his connection with this vital staple crop. Hun Hunahpu is the first child of the two oldest gods in the Maya pantheon, the
                Grandfather and the Grandmother. Though it might seem strange to have characters
                named One and Seven Hunahpu, the distinction has to do with Maya astronomy and their
                calendrical system. One would be the beginning of a cycle. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="SevH" inPV="true">
            <name>Seven Hunahpu</name>
            <img src="images/characterPics/One_and_7_Hun.jpg"/>
            <entity>God</entity>
            <family>
                <parents>
                    <mother idref="#Xmu">Xmucane</mother>
                    <father idref="#Xpi">Xpiyacoc</father>
                </parents>
                <brother idref="#OneH">One Hunahpu</brother>
                <nephews>
                    <nephew idref="#Hun">Hunahpu</nephew>
                    <nephew idref="#Xba">Xbalanque</nephew>
                    <nephew idref="#OneMonk">One Monkey</nephew>
                    <nephew idref="#OneArt">One Artisan</nephew>
                </nephews>
            </family>
            <desc>Seven Hunahpu is the second child of the two oldest gods in the Maya pantheon, the
                Grandfather and the Grandmother. Though his brother One Hunahpu fathers children, Seven Hunahpu never takes a wife and, according to the narrator, remains "a boy" and a mere uncle figure to his four nephews. He and his brother are very good at a traditional Mesoamerican ball game, and Seven Hunahpu spends most of his time on earth playing. He dies when One Death and Seven Death summon him and One Hunahpu to Xibalba for a match, and he and his brother fall for all the tricks of the Xibalban lords. After Hunahpu and Xbalanque's victory, they ask Seven Hunahpu to name the parts of his face so that he can "be put back together again" after his death. Though Seven Hunahpu can only name a few parts of his face, the twins leave their father and uncle buried in the ball court so they'll be able to be appropriately worshipped. Though it might seem strange to have characters
                named One and Seven Hunahpu, the distinction has to do with Maya astronomy and their
                calendrical system. Seven would be the end of the cycle. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="OneMonk" inPV="true">
            <name>One Monkey</name>
            <altName>One Batz</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/OneMonk_and_One_Art.jpg"/>
            <family>
                <parents>
                    <father idref="#OneH">One Hunahpu</father>
                    <mother>Xbaquiyalo</mother>
                </parents>
                <grandparents>
                    <grandma idref="#Xmu">Xmucane</grandma>
                    <grandpa idref="#Xpi">Xpiyacoc</grandpa>
                </grandparents>
                <brother idref="#OneArt">One Artisan</brother>
                <brother idref="#Hun">Hunahpu</brother>
                <brother idref="#Xba">Xbalanque</brother>
                <uncle idref="#SevH">Seven Hunahpu</uncle>
            </family>
            <desc>One Monkey is onne of the sons of One Hunahpu and Xbaquiyalo. Before One left for
                Xibalba to eventually be defeated, the two brothers trained One Monkey and One
                Artisan to be great artisans. With time they became accomplished flautists, singers,
                writers, carvers, jewelers, and metalworkers; even becoming quite wise.
                Unfortunately they were tortured souls, extremely jealous of Hunahpu and Xbalanque
                as their younger half-brothers were better than them at most everything. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="OneArt" inPV="true">
            <name>One Artisan</name>
            <altName>One Chouen</altName>
            <altName>One Howler</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/howler_Copan_sculpture.jpg"/>
            <family>
                <parents>
                    <father idref="#OneH">One Hunahpu</father>
                    <mother>Xbaquiyalo</mother>
                </parents>
                <grandparents>
                    <grandma idref="#Xmu">Xmucane</grandma>
                    <grandpa idref="#Xpi">Xpiyacoc</grandpa>
                </grandparents>
                <brother idref="#OneMonk">One Monkey</brother>
                <brother idref="#Hun">Hunahpu</brother>
                <brother idref="#Xba">Xbalanque</brother>
                <uncle idref="#SevH">Seven Hunahpu</uncle>
            </family>
            <desc>One Artisan is one the sons of One Hunahpu and Xbaquiyalo. Before One and Seven
                Hunahpu left for Xibalba to eventually be defeated, the two brothers trained One
                Monkey and One Artisan to be great artisans. With time they became accomplished
                flautists, singers, writers, carvers, jewelers, and metalworkers; even becoming
                quite wise. Unfortunately they were tortured souls, extremely jealous of Hunahpu and
                Xbalanque as their younger half-brothers were better than them at most everything.
            </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="LOX" inPV="true">
            <name>Lords of Xibalba</name>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Jasaw-Kawiil-bone_Xibalba.jpg"/>
            <of>Xibalba</of>
            <desc>The lords of Xibalba are the court that rules Xibalba, the underworld. The group
                as a whole is far from a charming lot, and tends to ultimately sacrifice all who
                come before them, either personally or by means of their six houses, each of which
                serves as trial. In order of highest to lowest rank the lords of Xibalba are: One
                and Seven Death, who are the ruler and second in charge of Xibalba; House Corner and
                Blood Gatherer, who draw blood from people; Pus Master and Jaundice Master,
                responsible for dispensing their respective namesakes; Bone Scepter and Skull
                Scepter, who cause people to become emaciated until they’re nothing but bones; Trash
                Master and Stab Master, who punish those with untidy doorways and patios by stabbing
                them; and Wing and Packstrap, who cause people to spontaneously die on roads. It is
                One and Seven Death who, angered by the sounds of the ball game played by One and
                Seven Hunahpu on the road to Xibalba, summon the twins to Xibalba to sacrifice them.
            The remaining residents of Xibalba are thought to have fallen under the dominion of one of these Lords, going about the face of the Earth to carry out their listed duties. 
            </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="OneD" inPV="true">
            <name>One Death</name>
            <img src="images/characterPics/one_death_godA.jpg"/>
            <entity>Lord</entity>
            <of>Xibalba</of>
            
            <desc>One Death is one of the most powerful lords of Xibalba, along with Seven Death.
                Both lords enjoy their peace and quiet, which leads them to summon One Hunahpu,
                Seven Hunahpu, Hunahpu, and Xbalanque to Xibalba in attempts to sacrifice them after
                they make too much noise playing their ball game. One Death is also a skilled
                trickster, and sets many traps for his potential victims. He does, however, attempt
                to magnify himself far beyond what he deserves, and this is his downfall. He dies
                when he's too entranced by Xbalanque and Hunahpu's return as minstrels to understand
                that they're actually going to kill him.</desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="SevenD" inPV="true">
            <name>Seven Death</name>
            <img src="images/characterPics/lords_of_xibalba.jpeg"/>
            <entity>Lord</entity>
            <of>Xibalba</of>
            <desc>Seven Death is a powerful lord of Xibalba who works primarily with One Death. The
                lords are skilled ball players, though they detest when non-Xibalban gods play ball,
                as it makes a great deal of noise in Xibalba. This leads One Death and Seven Death
                to summon ball players to Xibalba with the intention of putting an end to the noise.
                One and Seven Death are successful in tricking and killing One Hunahpu and Seven
                Hunahpu, but they are outsmarted time and again by One Hunahpu's sons, Hunahpu and
                Xbalanque.</desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="TOM" inPV="true">
            <name>The Owl Messengers</name>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Owls.jpg"/>
            <of>Xibalba</of>
            <desc>The four owl messengers of Xibalba, called Shooting Owl (“like a point, just
                piercing”), One-Legged Owl (“with just one leg; he has wings”), Macaw Owl (“with a
                red back; he has wings”), and Skull Owl (with only a head alone; he has no legs, but
                he does have wings). They are often referred to as Military Keepers of the Mat,
                which is their rank in Xibalba. The Owls are ordered by the lords of Xibalba to
                summon One Hunahpu and Seven Hunahpu to their defeat at Xibalba. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="BW" inPV="true">
            <name>Blood Woman</name>
            <altName>Little Blood</altName>
            <altName>Lady Blood</altName>
            <altName>Xquic</altName>
            <altName>Maiden</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/blood_woman.jpeg"/>
            <of>Xibalba</of>
            <family>
                <parents>
                    <father idref="#BldG">Blood Gatherer</father>
                </parents>
                <children>
                    <son idref="#Hun">Hunahpu</son>
                    <son idref="#Xba">Xbalanque</son>
                </children>
                <babydaddy idref="#OneH">One Hunahpu</babydaddy>
            </family>
            <desc>Blood Woman, or simply the Maiden, is the daughter of Blood Gatherer, the fourth
                lord of Xibalba. After being told by her father about the calabash tree under which
                One and Seven Hunahpu are buried, she decides to go to the tree to see its fruit.
                When the Maiden arrives at the tree, though, the decapitated head of One Hunahpu
                spits into her hand impregnating her with Hunahpu and Xbalanque. Six months into her
                virgin pregnancy, when the Maiden begins to show signs of her pregnancy the lords of
                Xibalba determine that she must be sacrificed and order their owl messengers to do
                so. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="BldG" inPV="true">
            <name>Blood Gatherer</name>
            <altName>Gathered Blood</altName>
            <altName>Cuchumaquic</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/bldGthr2.jpg"/>
            <entity>Lord</entity>
            <of>Xibalba</of>
            <family>
                <children>
                    <daughter idref="#BW">Lady Blood</daughter>
                </children>
                <grandChildren>
                    <grandson idref="#Hun">Hunahpu</grandson>
                    <grandson idref="#Xba">Xbalanque</grandson>
                </grandChildren>
            </family>
            <desc>Blood Gatherer is the fourth lord of Xibalba. He has a virgin daughter, Blood
                Moon, and is enraged when he realizes she's pregnant. Because he believes that her
                children will be bastards, he, One Death, and Seven Death command the owl messengers
                to take her into the woods and cut out her heart.</desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Toh" inPV="true">
            <name>Tohil</name>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Tohil.jpg"/>
            <entity>God</entity>
            <desc>Tohil is the patron god of the Quiché-Maya and the bringer of fire, which he
                creates by pivoting in his sandal. Tohil first appears by name in the fourth part of
                the story which outlines the lineage of man up until the writing of the Popol Vuh.
                Interestingly in Diego Rivera’s watercolors we see Tohil first appear in the
                creation of the universe. It’s slightly uncertain exactly what his connection to the
                inception of the earth may have been. Tohil is probably best known for being the
                first to ask the Quiché to perform sacrifice. But despite being a somewhat demanding
                god Tohil can also be quite benevolent. He saves the early men from dying from the
                cold by giving them fire. His mercy ends as soon as he believes he has been
                slighted, though. A rival tribe, the Cakchiquels, steals fire from the Quichébecause
                they too are dying from the cold. Tohil demands that the thieves be sacrificed, so
                as to embarrass their patron god, Calm Snake (who oddly enough has the appearance of
                a bat). </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Cha" inPV="false">
            <name>Chaac</name>
            <altName>Chahk</altName>
            <altName>Rain God</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/Chaac.jpg"/>
            <entity>Rain God</entity>
            <desc>
                Chaac is the goggled-eyed rain god, of prime importance to the Mayans. Chaac has a four-fold aspect, with each aspect representing the cardinal directions and colors. Chaac brought clouds, thunder, lightning and most importantly, rain.
            </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Itz" inPV="false">
            <name>Itzamna</name>
            <altName>Creation God</altName>
            <altName>God D</altName>
            <img src="images\characterPics\Itzamna.jpg"/>
            <entity>Creator God</entity>
            <desc>Itzamna is a creator god, one of the gods involved in creating human beings and father of the Bacabs, who upheld the corners of the world. Itzamna taught humans the crafts of writing and medicine. Itzamna is sometimes identified with the high god Hunab Ku and the sun god Kinich Ahau.</desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="GodG" inPV="false">
            <name>Kinich Ahau</name>
            <altName>Sun God</altName>
            <altName>K'inich Ajaw</altName>
            <altName>God G</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/godG.jpg"/>
            <entity>God</entity>
            <desc>Kinich Ahau is the sun god of the Mayans, sometimes associated with or an aspect of Itzamna. During the Classic period, Kinich Ahau was used as a royal title, carrying the idea of the divine king. He is also known in the Mayan codices as God G and is shown in many carvings on Mayan pyramids.</desc>
        </character>
        
        <character xml:id="GodL" inPV="false">
            <name>God L of the Underworld</name>
            <img src="images/characterPics/God-L.jpg"/>
            <entity>Underworld God</entity>
            <of>Xibalba</of>
            <desc>The name of this Maya Pantheon deity is unknown. What we do know, is that he is related to the night and the underworld, as well as death and the moment of creation of the cosmos. As in the other powerful gods of the Maya culture, his image is represented through an old man with jaguar ears and black painted body parts.  
                
                One of the most distinctive features of this god is a kind of hat decorated with owl feathers of the horned species. His back is covered by a huge jaguar skin or he appears naked showing the flaccidity of his belly. </desc>
        </character>
        <character xml:id="Kaw" inPV="false">
            <name>K'awiil</name>
            <altName>God K</altName>
            <img src="images/characterPics/godK_kawiil-scepter.jpg"/>
            <entity>God</entity>
            <desc>
                Kʼawiil, in the Post-Classic codices corresponding to God K, is a Maya deity identified with lightning, serpents, fertility and maize. He is characterized by a zoomorphic head, with large eyes, long, upturned snout and attenuated serpent tooth.[1] A torch, stone celt, or cigar, normally emitting smoke, comes out of his forehead, while a serpent leg represents a lightning bolt. In this way, Kʼawiil personifies the lightning axe both of the rain deity and of the king as depicted on his stelae. 
            </desc>
        </character>
    </index>
</xml>
